# TREVOR VINCENT, PHD

(+1) 416 738 6934 ♦ trevor.j.vincent@gmail.com ♦ trevorvincent.com ♦ github.com/trevor-vincent

#### **HIGHLIGHTS**

Independent problem solver and researcher with lots of experience presenting scientific work (20+ presentations) and communicating to audiences of different expertise. Currently working on multiple novel projects in the field of machine learning and artificial intelligence.

Experienced C++,C and python programmer (over 100,000 lines+ in each) with expert-level knowledge in numerical solution techniques for partial differential equations and a broad knowledge of machine learning algorithms.

Two years of experience working with a Nobel-prize winning scientific collaboration (LIGO; ligo.org), analyzing time series data and writing simulation software.

Four years of experience working with a team of 10+ programmers developing a next-generation code for upcoming exa-scale supercomputers.

Chess master (title earned in 2008). Former Manitoba chess champion (six consecutive times) and former Canadian scholastic chess champion.

#### CURRENT PROJECTS

## **Preconditioning Gradient Descent**

Nov. 2019 - Now

- · Speeding up NN learning is a very important.
- · One method for speeding up the learning rate is by preconditioning gradient descent
- e.g. https://arxiv.org/abs/1902.02257
- · With my knowledge of numerical solution methods for elliptic partial differential equations, I have gained a large expertise in preconditioning methods. I am now working on novel preconditioning methods to speed up learning rates for NNs.

# Adversarial Attacks on Neural Networks

July 2019 - Now

- · Neural Networks and other machine-learning models are vulnerable to adversarial attacks.
- · I've developed a gradient-free genetic algorithm based on https://arxiv.org/abs/1805.11090 to find vulnerabilities in black-box machine-learning models.

#### Chess Puzzle Composition using GANs

Aug. 2019 - Now

- · Composing aesthetic chess puzzles is a difficult problem in the field of computer creativity.
- · No one has tried composing chess puzzles using a machine learning approach.
- · I'm working on a code called DeepChessComposer which currently uses an autoencoder ("Pos2Vec") trained on a large database of chess positions and a Generative Adversarial Network to compose chess puzzles.

# N-player No-Limit Texas Holdem Poker using ML approaches

Sept. 2019 - Now

- · Machine-learning approaches have shown great promise for heads-up (two-player) no-limit poker (e.g. DeepStack).
- $\cdot$  No work has been done to try and extend these 2-player machine learning approaches to 6 or 9-player No-Limit Hold-em Poker (or the general case of N-players).
- · I'm currently working on an N-player extension to the two-player Texas Holdem engine DeepStack (https://www.deepstack.ai/).

#### **EXPERIENCE**

# Canadian Institute for Theoretical Astrophysics

Sept. 2013 - Aug. 2019

PhD Researcher in Computational Astrophysics

- · Developed next generation numerical methods for solving the Einstein field equations (a non-linear set of partial differential equations) on supercomputers and implemented them in a  $\sim 200,000$ -line code available on GitHub.
- · Worked on a team (10+developers) to develop a task-based parallelism framework for numerical relativity called SpECTRE, available on GitHub.
- · Member of the LIGO collaboration, working on extracting neutrino and matter emission properties from gravitational wave and electromagnetic counterpart signals of binary neutron star mergers.

# University of Winnipeg

2009-2013

Summer Research Scientist

- · Developed a state-of-art GPU-accelerated (via CUDA) C++ code for the diffusion and collision of water molecules around randomly oriented axons in 3d brain-matter. This was coupled with a numerical solve of the Bloch partial differential equations to obtain the magnetic resonance imaging signal in realistic environments.
- · Developed a Markov chain Monte Carlo code for estimating axon distribution properties from magnetic resonance imaging signals signals.
- · Used machine learning techniques to study brain changes in mice with different Alzheimer-based gene modifications.

#### **EDUCATION**

# University of Toronto, Toronto, ON

Sept. 2013 - August 2019

PhD in Physics, specializing in computational astrophysics. PhD work was funded by an NSERC CGSD scholarship (\$105,000) and a NSERC CGSM scholarship (\$30,000).

Advisor: Prof. Harald Pfeiffer

# University of Winnipeg, Winnipeg, MB

Sept 2008 - Sept 2013

Bachelors of Science in Physics. Undergraduate work was funded by 15 scholarships. Winner of the Governor Generals Silver Medal for highest graduating GPA in the university.

### **SKILLS**

Highly Proficient C++, C, MPI, CUDA, Bash, Git, CMake, Emacs, GDB, LaTeX

Python (Pandas, Matplotlib, scikit-learn, tensorflow, keras, etc)

Substantial Experience OpenCL, Matlab, Mathematica, HDF5, Paraview, Visit,

SQL, HTML, OpenMP, TravisCI, Jenkins

Working Knowledge Java, Fortran, Hadoop, Spark

Vincent, Trevor, Harald P. Pfeiffer, and Nils L. Fischer. "hp-adaptive discontinuous Galerkin solver for elliptic equations in numerical relativity." Physical Review D 100, no. 8 (2019): 084052. arXiv preprint arXiv:1907.01572.

Vincent, Trevor, Francois Foucart, Matthew D. Duez, Roland Haas, Lawrence E. Kidder, Harald P. Pfeiffer, and Mark A. Scheel. "Unequal Mass Binary Neutron Star Simulations with Neutrino Transport: Ejecta and Neutrino Emission." arXiv preprint arXiv:1908.00655. Submitted to Physical Review D. (2019).

Hinderer, Tanja, Samaya Nissanke, Francois Foucart, Kenta Hotokezaka, Trevor Vincent, Mansi Kasliwal, Patricia Schmidt et al. "Distinguishing the nature of comparable-mass neutron star binary systems with multimessenger observations: GW170817 case study." Physical Review D 100, no. 6 (2019): 063021. arXiv preprint arXiv:1808.03836.

Kidder, Lawrence E., Scott E. Field, Francois Foucart, Erik Schnetter, Saul A. Teukolsky, Andy Bohn, Trevor Vincent et al. "SpECTRE: A task-based discontinuous Galerkin code for relativistic astrophysics." Journal of Computational Physics 335 (2017): 84-114.

Mercredi, Morgan, Trevor J. Vincent, Christopher P. Bidinosti, and Melanie Martin. "Assessing the accuracy of using oscillating gradient spin echo sequences with AxCaliber to infer micron-sized axon diameters." Magnetic Resonance Materials in Physics, Biology and Medicine 30, no. 1 (2017): 1-14.

Hayes, Kerrie, Richard Buist, Trevor J. Vincent, Jonathan D. Thiessen, Yanbo Zhang, Handi Zhang, Junhui Wang et al. "Comparison of manual and semi-automated segmentation methods to evaluate hippocampus volume in APP and PS1 transgenic mice obtained via in vivo magnetic resonance imaging." Journal of neuroscience methods 221 (2014): 103-111.

Thiessen, Jonathan D., Trevor J. Vincent, Sheryl L. Herrera, and Melanie Martin. "Diffusion Tensor Metric Measurements as a Function of Diffusion Time in the Rat central nervous system." Magnetic Resonance Insights 5 (2012): MRI-S10692. 5:3747.

Vincent, Trevor J., Jonathan D. Thiessen, Laryssa M. Kurjewicz, Shelley L. Germscheid, Allan J. Turner, Peter Zhilkin, Murray E. Alexander, and Melanie Martin. "Longitudinal brain size measurements in APP/PS1 transgenic mice." Magnetic Resonance Insights 4 (2010): MRI-S5885.

## SELECTED AWARDS

NSERC CGSD Scholarship (\$105000)	2015
NSERC CGSM Scholarship (\$30000)	2014
Governor Generals Silver Medal	2013
CIHR Undergraduate Research Award (\$5000)	2013
NSERC Undergraduate Research Award (\$5000)	2012
NSERC Undergraduate Research Award (\$5000)	2011
NSERC Undergraduate Research Award (\$5000)	2010